<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Methylene Blue</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Methylene Blue</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>programutox@disroot.org (Programutox)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>programutox@disroot.org (Programutox)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Programutox (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 12:39:02 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Open source apps I&#39;m using</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/open-source-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 12:39:02 +0200</pubDate><author>programutox@disroot.org (Programutox)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/open-source-apps/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I will present open source apps that I use on my mobile phone. My first motivation was that I accidentally removed Google Play store and service using adb. So I had to find alternatives. I was looking for open source and straightforward applications, so that they are lightweight.&#xA;App stores First, I was using F-Droid, but loading updates was slow, and for some apps you had to add external links, which behave like plugins.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>I will present open source apps that I use on my mobile phone.
My first motivation was that I accidentally removed Google Play store and service using adb.
So I had to find alternatives. I was looking for open source and straightforward applications, so that they are lightweight.</p>
<h2 id="app-stores">App stores</h2>
<p>First, I was using <a href="https://f-droid.org/">F-Droid</a>, but loading updates was slow, and for some apps you had to add external links, which behave
like plugins.</p>
<p>By digging on AlternativeTo, I found <a href="https://github.com/NeoApplications/Neo-Store">NeoStore</a>, which is an F-Droid client with a modern UI and
more features. I heard about <a href="https://apt.izzysoft.de/fdroid/">IzzyDroid</a>, but I haven&rsquo;t used it yet.</p>
<p>Next, I found <a href="https://github.com/ImranR98/Obtainium">Obtainium</a>, which allows you to install apps from their repository (Github, Gitlab, F-Droid).
Since in general, Github releases are more frequent than F-Droid, your apps will be more up-to-date. However, Obtainium is still in beta, so you might
find some bugs.</p>
<p>Finally, if you&rsquo;d like to install other applications, two words : Aurora Store. It&rsquo;s FOSS and you don&rsquo;t have to connect to your Google account to install applications.
And the timing is perfect, you can install it using Obtainium.</p>
<h3 id="for-xiaomi-users">For Xiaomi users</h3>
<p>If you have a Xiaomi smartphone and you want to use NeoStore and/or Obtainium, you have to <strong>disable MIUI optimizations</strong>.</p>
<p>Here are the steps :</p>
<ol>
<li>Go to <code>Settings &gt; About phone</code>, and press the button &ldquo;MIUI version&rdquo; multiple times, until you get the message &ldquo;You are now a developer&rdquo;.</li>
<li>No go to <code>Settings &gt; Additionnal settings &gt; Developer options</code>.</li>
<li>Scroll down, there should be an option &ldquo;Disable MIUI optimizations&rdquo;. If not, in the Auto-fill section, tap multiple times on &ldquo;Reset tp default
values&rdquo;. Then you should find the desired option.</li>
<li>You will get a warning, tick the box, wait 10 seconds and press OK.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="apps-im-using">Apps I&rsquo;m using</h2>
<p>All of them can be installed using Obtainium.</p>
<h3 id="imagesopen-source-appsadawaypng-adaway-imagesopen-source-appsadawaypng"><img src="/images/open-source-apps/adaway.png"> AdAway <img src="/images/open-source-apps/adaway.png"></h3>
<p><a href="https://github.com/AdAway/AdAway">AdAway</a> is a lightweight ad blocker. If your phone is non-rooted, it will use a VPN, else it will rewrite hosts file, which will be more optimized.
The downside is that, as it uses a VPN, you can&rsquo;t use other apps which work the same way, such as <a href="https://github.com/M66B/NetGuard">NetGuard</a> or
<a href="https://riseup.net/en/vpn/android">RiseupVPN</a> (probably the only free VPN that is legit).</p>
<p>Similar apps : <a href="https://github.com/blokadaorg/blokada">Blokada</a>, it lets you choose what kind of ads and trackers you want to block, but slows down
much more your Internet connection.</p>
<h3 id="imagesopen-source-appsamazepng-amaze-file-manager-imagesopen-source-appsamazepng"><img src="/images/open-source-apps/amaze.png"> Amaze File Manager <img src="/images/open-source-apps/amaze.png"></h3>
<p><a href="https://github.com/TeamAmaze/AmazeFileManager">Amaze File Manager</a> is a well-designed and highly customizable file manager.</p>
<h3 id="ente-auth">Ente Auth</h3>
<p>Cross-platform.</p>
<p>Similar App : <a href="https://github.com/beemdevelopment/Aegis">Aegis Authenticator</a> (Android only).</p>
<h3 id="imagesopen-source-appsavespng-aves-imagesopen-source-appsavespng"><img src="/images/open-source-apps/aves.png"> Aves <img src="/images/open-source-apps/aves.png"></h3>
<p><a href="https://github.com/deckerst/aves">Aves</a> is an image and video gallery.</p>
<p>Before this, I was using Simple Gallery, and was pretty satisfied with it. However, Simple Mobile Tools got bought by a company, which then added
ads.</p>
<h3 id="birday">Birday</h3>
<p>Instead of taking notes of your relatives&rsquo; birthdays, you can write them on <a href="https://github.com/m-i-n-a-r/birday">Birday</a>. It will gives you more
information (age, astrological sign) and notify you when it&rsquo;s someone&rsquo;s birthday. You can also set reminders that notify you a few days before.</p>
<h3 id="bitwarden">Bitwarden</h3>
<p>Freemium password manager.</p>
<h3 id="clima">Clima</h3>
<p>Get your meteo without having to indicate your geolocation. Has a black theme for AMOLED screens.</p>
<h3 id="imagesopen-source-appscromitepng-cromite-imagesopen-source-appscromitepng"><img src="/images/open-source-apps/cromite.png"> Cromite <img src="/images/open-source-apps/cromite.png"></h3>
<p>Bromite&rsquo;s last release is from 19 december 2022. So a fork has been created, <a href="https://github.com/uazo/cromite">Cromite</a>.</p>
<h3 id="fairemail">FairEmail</h3>
<p>Best email client.</p>
<h3 id="feeder">Feeder</h3>
<p>Cool RSS feed reader.</p>
<h3 id="imagesopen-source-appsfloccuspng-floccus-imagesopen-source-appsfloccuspng"><img src="/images/open-source-apps/floccus.png"> Floccus <img src="/images/open-source-apps/floccus.png"></h3>
<p>A bookmark manager. To sync bookmarks, you need a nextcloud provider. Mine is <a href="https://disroot.org/fr/services/nextcloud">disroot</a>.
There is also an extension, which updates directly your browser bookmarks.</p>
<h3 id="fossify-messages">Fossify Messages</h3>
<p>Simple, private messages.</p>
<h3 id="imagesopen-source-appsheliboardpng-heliboard-imagesopen-source-appsheliboardpng"><img src="/images/open-source-apps/heliboard.png"> HeliBoard <img src="/images/open-source-apps/heliboard.png"></h3>
<p><a href="https://github.com/Helium314/HeliBoard">HeliBoard</a> is a fork of OpenBoard.</p>
<h3 id="huggingassist">HuggingAssist</h3>
<p>A HuggingChat client.</p>
<h3 id="mupdf-viewer">MuPDF viewer</h3>
<p>A simple, effective PDF reader. However pages become dark then light each time you change pages or zoom in/out.
If you know a better PDF viewer, feel free to send me a mail. I&rsquo;ll add here.</p>
<h3 id="olauncher-clutter-free">Olauncher Clutter Free</h3>
<p>A minimalist launcher, which removes ads, links from Olauncher and does not require Internet connection.</p>
<h3 id="opencontacts">OpenContacts</h3>
<h3 id="oss-docs-scanner">OSS Docs Scanner</h3>
<p>You take a photo, the app automatically detects document&rsquo;s border, and you can convert to pdf. Note that the app is updated VERY regularly.</p>
<h3 id="quillpad">Quillpad</h3>
<p>Take notes using Markdown.</p>
<h3 id="simplex-chat">SimpleX Chat</h3>
<p>Explain about Signal, Session, AlternativeTo etc.</p>
<h3 id="misc">Misc.</h3>
<p>Koler, Calculator, Camera.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Useful Websites</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/useful-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 19:10:06 +0100</pubDate><author>programutox@disroot.org (Programutox)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/useful-websites/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Here are some websites that seem situational, but turn out to be very nice when you know them.&#xA;Summary Anglish AlternativeTo Chadnet Cheatography Codewars Coolors DeepL Flaticon Haveibeenpwned HuggingChat JustDeleteMe Ninite OpenGameArt Pixabay Portapps Sample Focus Spyware Watchdog Wikiwand Anglish Anglish promotes linguistical purism (i.e. preferring use of anglo-saxon expressions and limit borrowing from other languages), but I use it personally to improve my English vocabulary. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit like, in France, looking for French words to replace anglicisms.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Here are some websites that seem situational, but turn out to be very nice when you know them.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#anglish">Anglish</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#alternativeto">AlternativeTo</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#chadnet">Chadnet</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#cheatography">Cheatography</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#codewars">Codewars</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#coolors">Coolors</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#deepl">DeepL</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#flaticon">Flaticon</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#haveibeenpwned">Haveibeenpwned</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#huggingchat">HuggingChat</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#justdeleteme">JustDeleteMe</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#ninite">Ninite</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#opengameart">OpenGameArt</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#pixabay">Pixabay</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#portapps">Portapps</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#sample-focus">Sample Focus</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#spyware-watchdog">Spyware Watchdog</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#wikiwand">Wikiwand</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="anglish">Anglish</h2>
<p><a href="https://anglish.org/wiki/Anglish">Anglish</a> promotes linguistical purism (i.e. preferring use of anglo-saxon expressions and limit borrowing from
other languages), but I use it personally to improve my English vocabulary. It&rsquo;s a bit like, in France, looking for French words to replace anglicisms.</p>
<p><img alt="A table showing anglo-saxon expressions to prefer" src="/images/useful-websites/anglish.png"></p>
<h2 id="alternativeto">AlternativeTo</h2>
<p><a href="https://alternativeto.net/">AlternativeTo</a> gives you alternatives to softwares, applications, games and websites.</p>
<p>For example, you can look for alternatives to Adobe Premiere Pro, and refine results using filters. Thanks to these, you can choose to display only
open source softwares available on Linux, or ones that are specialized in visual effects, free and available on Windows.
Oddly enough, you can&rsquo;t choose at the same time free and open source filters.</p>
<p>There is a <a href="https://alternativeto.net/news/all/">News</a> category to stay informed about softwares/apps releases, companies or developers.
A <a href="https://feed.alternativeto.net/news/all/">RSS feed</a> is also provided, which is very appreciable.</p>
<p><img alt="AlternativeTo offers a description and alternatives to Adobe Premiere Pro" src="/images/useful-websites/alternativeto.png"></p>
<p><img alt="AlternativeTo offers an article on the deal between Google and Epic Games" src="/images/useful-websites/alternativeto_news.png"></p>
<h2 id="chadnet">Chadnet</h2>
<p><a href="https://wiki.chadnet.org/">Chadnet</a> has a collection of articles and websites focused on several areas : History, science, health, etc..
If you&rsquo;re looking for a good read, go for it.</p>
<p>⚠️ Some articles are not checked, so you&rsquo;ll have to be careful.</p>
<p><img alt="Chadnet homepage" src="/images/useful-websites/chadnet.png"></p>
<p><img alt="Chadnet offers a blood donation and transfusion table" src="/images/useful-websites/chadnet_table.png"></p>
<h2 id="cheatography">Cheatography</h2>
<p><a href="https://cheatography.com/">Cheatography</a> gathers <em>cheatsheets</em>, which are images, texts and schematics explaining briefly concepts, a bit like
revision sheets.</p>
<p>Although the majority is in English, you can still find cheatsheets in other languages in this website.</p>
<p><img alt="A cheatsheet about atoms family" src="/images/useful-websites/cheatography.png"></p>
<h2 id="codewars">Codewars</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.codewars.com/">Codewars</a> offers programming problems (also known as &ldquo;katas&rdquo;). Perfect for training since it is concrete and fun.
You choose the programming langages you wan to progress with, then progression mode (learn the basics, practice and repeat, rank up).
Note that you have to create an account.</p>
<p>Katas&rsquo; difficulty is expressed in kyu. A kata with 3 kyu will be more complex than one with 5 kyu.</p>
<p><img alt="CodeWars homepage once you logged in" src="/images/useful-websites/codewars.png"></p>
<h2 id="coolors">Coolors</h2>
<p><a href="https://coolors.co/generate">Coolors</a> generates five complementary colors for you. This can be very helpful when you make websites,
reports <del>or Geometry Dash levels</del>.</p>
<p>If you are not satisfied with the color palette, but one or more of them appeal to you, you can lock them, so that next palettes use these coolors as well.
Finally, when a palette suits you, it is possible to generate a permanent link to access it next times.</p>
<p><img alt="Here I have the following complementary colors : dark green, less dark green, white, orange, and pink-purple" src="/images/useful-websites/coolors.png"></p>
<h2 id="deepl">DeepL</h2>
<p>This is probably the most well-known website on this list but I wanted to mention it.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.deepl.com/translator">DeepL Translator</a> is a translator that, unlike Google&rsquo;s one, has a better understanding of expressions and avoids word-by-word translation.
Obviously it is not perfect, this is the reason why I advise to check translations with other translators as well, like <a href="https://libretranslate.com/">LibreTranslate</a> (<a href="https://translate.disroot.org/">disroot</a>).
I like this one, as it is open source and easily usable with JavaScript. Nevertheless, it is more word-by-word, and gives translations sometimes nonsensical.
So be careful.</p>
<p><img alt="Traduction example with the expression &ldquo;je suis à l&rsquo;aise dans mes nouvelles pompes&rdquo;" src="/images/useful-websites/deepl.png"></p>
<p>Here, the correct translation is &ldquo;I feel comfortable in my new shoes&rdquo;, and not &ldquo;pumps&rdquo;.</p>
<p><strong>Note :</strong> DeepL does not have dark theme, I use <a href="https://darkreader.org/">Dark Reader</a> to have one.</p>
<h2 id="flaticon">Flaticon</h2>
<p>Flaticon gathers vectorized images. Ideal when you are looking for icons, images or logos for a vidéo or a game. However you have to credit the authors.</p>
<p>There is also <a href="https://www.freepik.com/">Freepik</a> (in fact, it was Freepik that created Flaticon), which has photos, videos and models, but free assets
are more limited.</p>
<p><img alt="Flaticon shows me emojis" src="/images/useful-websites/flaticon.png"></p>
<h2 id="haveibeenpwned">Haveibeenpwned</h2>
<p><a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/">Haveibeenpwned</a> check if the email address you entered was exposed to data leak.
If so, it will show the impacted websites and you will have to modify your passwords.
This also works with phone numbers.</p>
<p><img alt="What is displayed when your email address has not leaked" src="/images/useful-websites/haveibeenpwned.png">
<img alt="What is displayed when your email address has leaked" src="/images/useful-websites/haveibeenpwned2.png"></p>
<h2 id="huggingchat">HuggingChat</h2>
<p>Do you know ChatGPT ? Don&rsquo;t you find his answers sometimes strange ? Hesitating to take out a subscription to GPT-4?</p>
<p>Save 20$ per month and use <a href="https://huggingface.co/chat/">HuggingChat</a>.
Not only it allows you to choose the chat model (the default one, MistralAI, is already very good) but it also gives you better answers in general,
and has a better tone. Moreover, you don&rsquo;t have to log in to chat, and if you reach the message limit, you can erase cookies to lift it.</p>
<p><img alt="I ask HuggingChat how is called the rectangle in which you can write text, because I can&rsquo;t remember" src="/images/useful-websites/huggingchat-en.png"></p>
<p>The only downside is that by default MistralAI tends to give a substantial amount of text, even you ask him to give you short answers.
You can fix that either by switching to another chat model (like Gemini) or by modifying the <em>system prompt</em>.
To do so, create a new chat, click on the gear icon next to the model name, then in the text box, write that you want the answers to be as simple as possible.</p>
<h2 id="justdeleteme">JustDeleteMe</h2>
<p><a href="https://justdeleteme.xyz/">JustDeleteMe</a> gives information about deletion of web service account. It indicates difficulty and steps, visible when clicking on <code>&quot;Show Info...&quot;</code>.
What I appreciate with this website is its straightforwardness. For instance, to delete a Facebook account you need to go to go through the settings
from top to bottom (hiding on purpose options like this is called a <strong>dark pattern</strong>). JustDeleteMe just gives you the link, with the chain icon.</p>
<p>Of course, not all websites are here, but in you don&rsquo;t find one you can <a href="https://github.com/jdm-contrib/jdm">contribute</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="JusteDeleteMe shows me how to delete a Twitter account" src="/images/useful-websites/justdeleteme.png"></p>
<h2 id="ninite">Ninite</h2>
<p><a href="https://ninite.com/">Ninite</a> allows you to install and update several softwares at once, quickly and easily. Very useful when you just bought or reset a PC.</p>
<p>Note that this service is Windows-only. On MacOS&rsquo; side, there are <a href="https://macapps.link/">macapps.link</a> and, to a lesser extent, <a href="https://setapp.com/fr">Setapp</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="Ninite offers a myriad of softwares" src="/images/useful-websites/ninite.png"></p>
<h2 id="opengameart">OpenGameArt</h2>
<p><a href="https://opengameart.org/">OpenGameArt</a> is full of free assets (images, textures, sound effects, musics) which can be used for video games. However,
you have to been careful with licenses : sometimes you must credit the author, other times you are not allowed to modify/remix the content.</p>
<p><img alt="I like looking for musics on OpenGameArt" src="/images/useful-websites/opengameart.png"></p>
<h2 id="pixabay">Pixabay</h2>
<p><a href="https://pixabay.com/fr">Pixabay</a> offers royalty free images. Very useful for illustrating reports, websites or videos.
Other similar websites exist, such as <a href="https://www.pexels.com/fr-fr/">Pexels</a> and <a href="https://unsplash.com/fr">Unsplash</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="Images representing science offered by Pixabay" src="/images/useful-websites/pixabay.png"></p>
<h2 id="portapps">Portapps</h2>
<p><a href="https://portapps.io/apps/">Portapps</a> gathers portable softwares, which don&rsquo;t need any complex installation (there is only one path, one repertory containing the program and necessary files) nor require pas de admin rights.
You can store them in a USB key and use them on other PCs without any problem.</p>
<p><img alt="You can find Android Studio, Brave and more on Portapps" src="/images/useful-websites/portapps.png"></p>
<p>There is also <a href="https://portableapps.com/">PortableApps</a>, more complete but with more specific softwares as well.</p>
<p><img alt="PortableApps offers a portable version of Paint.NET" src="/images/useful-websites/portableapps.png"></p>
<h2 id="sample-focus">Sample Focus</h2>
<p><a href="https://samplefocus.com">SampleFocus</a> allows you to find royalty free samples, and attribution is not required. However you will have a limited number of downloads per week.</p>
<p><img alt="Some samples offered by SampleFocus" src="/images/useful-websites/samplefocus.png"></p>
<h2 id="spyware-watchdog">Spyware Watchdog</h2>
<p><a href="https://spyware.neocities.org/articles/">Spyware Watchdog</a> gathers articles reviewing popular services and determine whether these are spywares or not.
Also its definition of <em>spyware</em> is a bit fussy, it is nonetheless fascinating to find out what softwares we use regularly do behind our back.</p>
<p><img alt="An article about Opera web browser" src="/images/useful-websites/spyware_watchdog.png"></p>
<h2 id="wikiwand">Wikiwand</h2>
<p>Wikiwand enables to read Wikipedia articles with a more modern and customizable interface.
You can adjust the theme, size, text width and align. A change from Wikipedia&rsquo;s austere (but sober) appearance.</p>
<p>Furthermore, Wikiwand uses AI pour to sum up or list the top facts about articles. You can hide this panel by clicking on the three dots on the right
then on &ldquo;Hide AI brief panel&rdquo; (even if it&rsquo;s in gray, you can click on it).</p>
<p><img alt="Wikipedia article about Monte Carlo Method" src="/images/useful-websites/wikipedia-en.png"></p>
<p><img alt="Same article but on Wikiwand, in which I modified the theme and display" src="/images/useful-websites/wikiwand-en.png"></p>
<p>Additionally, an addon exists, which redirects automatically Wikipedia pages you visit to Wikiwand, but I don&rsquo;t recommend it, as it collects <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/privacy/comments/m9ugpu/psa_the_browser_extension_wikiwand_is_collecting/">more data than necessary</a>
<a href="https://archive.is/za01X">[archive]</a>.
Also, Wikiwand displays ads if you don&rsquo;t use the addon, so if it bothers you, use an ad blocker like uBlock Origin ou, ideally, uMatrix.</p>
<p><a href="/blog/useful-websites/#introduction">Back to top</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
